经过数年，许多自然的密码学机制被发现是不安全的
Over the years many natural cryptographic
constructions were found to be insecure.
因此，现代密码学是一门严谨的科学
In response, modern cryptography was
developed as a rigorous science where
其中的机制总是有其安全性证明
constructions are always accompanied by a
proof of security. The language used to
用来描述证明的语言依赖于离散概率
在本小节和接下来的一节中
describe security relies on discrete
probability. In this segment and the next,
我会简要回顾一下离散概率的内容
I'll give a brief overview of discrete
probability, and I point to this Wiki
这篇维基百科文章介绍得更详细些
books article over here for a longer
introduction. Discrete probability is
离散概率定义在全局上，全局记为U
always defined over a universe which I'll
denote by U and this universe in our case
这里U总为有限集
事实上全局最常见的情况是
is always going to be a finite set. In
fact very commonly our universe is going
全体n位二进制串的集合
记为｛0,1｝^n
to be simply the set of all n bit strings
which here is denoted by zero one to the
举个例子,｛0,1｝^2表示2位0，1字符串
n. So for example the set zero one squared
is the set of all two bit strings which
包括00，01，10，11
happens to be the string zero, zero, zero
one, One, zero, and one, one. So there are
所以这个集合有4个元素，更一般地
在集合｛0,1｝^N中
four elements in this set, and more
generally in the set zero one to the N,
有2的N次方个元素
现在，在全局U上的概率分布
there are two to the N elements. Now a
probability distribution over this
为一函数，记为P
universe U is simply a function which I'll
denote by P, and this function, what it
该函数为全局中的每一个元素赋值
范围在0和1之间
does, is it assigns to every element in
the universe a number between zero and
这个数我称为全局中特定元素的权重或概率
one. And this number is what I'll call the
weight or the probability of that
这个函数P只有一个要求
particular element in the universe. Now
there's only one requirement on this
所有权重和为1
function P, and that is that the sum of
all the weights, sum up to one. That is,
如果我把全局中所有元素X的概率相加
if I sum the probability of all elements X
in the universe, what I end up with is the
最终得到1。那么我们来看一个非常简单的例子
关于全体2位字符串
number one. So let's look at a very simple
example looking back to our 2-bit
00，01，10，11
你可以考虑如下概率分布
universe. So 00, 01, ten and eleven. And you
can consider the following probability
例如，P(00)=1/2
distribution, which, for example, assigns
to the element 00, the probability one
P(01)=1/8
half. The elements 01, we assign the
probability 1/8th, to ten we assign the
P(10)=1/4, P(11)=1/8
probability one quarter and to eleven we
assign the probability 1/8th. Okay we can
好的，如果我们把这些数加起来，得1
see that if we sum up these numbers in
fact we get one which means that this
意味着这个概率P满足概率分布条件
probability P is in fact the probability
distribution. Now what these number mean
这些数的意义是，如果我从中取样本
is that if I sample from this probability
distribution I'll get the string 00 with
我以1/2概率得到00，以1/8概率得到01
probability one half I'll get the string
01 with probability 1/8th and so on and so
等等。那么现在我们理解了什么是概率分布
forth. So now that we understand what a
probability distribution is, let's look at
我们看两个概率分布的经典例子
two classic examples of probability
distributions. The first one is what's
第一个叫均匀分布
均匀分布为全局中的每一个元素
called the uniform distribution. The
uniform distribution assigns to every
分配了严格相同的权重
记|U|为全局U的大小
element in the universe, exactly the same
weight. I'm gonna use U between two bars
也就是全局里元素的个数
to denote the size of the universe U. That
is the number of elements in the universe,
由于我们希望概率和为1
and since we want the sum of all the
weights to sum out to one, and we want all
我们还希望所有权重一样
意味着对全局中每一个元素X
these weights to be equal, what this means
is that for every element X in the
我们赋予其概率1/|U|
如果我们看我们的例子
universe, we assign a probability of one
over U. So in particular if we look at our
2位字符串集合上的均匀分布
example, the uniform distribution and the
set of two [inaudible] strings, would
对每个字符串赋值1/4概率
simply assign one-quarter the weight,
one-quarter to each one of these strings
显然，这些权重的和为1
And clearly that, the sum of all the
weights sums up to one. Well again, what
这意味着如果我从这个分布中取样
this means is that if I sample at random
from this distribution, I'll get a uniform
我取到各个2位字符串的机会均等。
所以所有这些4位字符串在该分布中
sample across all our 2-bit strings. So all
of these 4-bit strings are equally likely
采样几率都一样。
另一个非常常见的分布是
to be sampled by this distribution.
Another distribution that's very common is
点分布，于某点X0
点分布的意义是
what's called a point distribution at the
point X0 And what this point distribution
把所有权重放在一个点上，比如X0
does is basically it puts all the weight
on a single point, namely X0. So here we
这里我们赋予X0所有权重1
对于全局中的其他点
assign to the point X0 all the weight, one
And then to all other points in the
我们赋予权重0
顺便一说，我想指出
universe, we assign the weight zero. And by
the way, I want to point out that this,
这个倒着的A表示任意
这是说，对所有点X
inverted, A here should be read as, for
all. So all this says is, that for all X
若其不为X0，则其概率为0
that are not equal to X zero, the
probability of that X is zero. So again
回到点分布的例子
going back to our example a point
distribution for example, that would put
将全部质量放在字符串10上
10的概率为1
all its mass on the string 1-0, would
assign probability one to the string 1-0
其他字符串概率为0
如果我从这个分布中取样很多次
and zero to all other strings. So now if I
sample from this distribution pretty much
我保证每次都是10，绝不会是其他字符串
I'm always guaranteed to always sample the
string 1-0 and never sample any of the
我们知道分布是什么。我最后想说
other strings. So now we know what a
distribution is, and I just want to make
由于全局U总是有限集
one last point, and that is that because
this universe U is always gonna be a
我们可以写下分配给
finite set up for us, we can actually
write down the weights that the
U中每个元素的权重
整个分布可表示成
distribution assigns to every element in
U, and represent the entire distribution
向量的形式。比如，如果你看3位字符串
as a vector. So, here for example, if you
look at the universe of an all 3-bit
我们可以写下赋予字符串000的概率
strings, we can literally write down the
ways that the distribution assigns to the
写下赋予001的概率，等等
string 000, then the way that distribution
assigns to the string 001 And so on, and
我们可以把这个写成一个向量
so forth. We you can see that we can write
this as a vector, in this case it will be
这里向量是8维的，3位字符串有8个
a vector of dimension eight, there will
be, there are eight strings of 3-bits as a
整个分布由8个实数来表示
result basically the entire distribution
is captured by this vector of eight real
范围从0到1
我想做的下一件事是定义事件
numbers, in the range of all zero to one.
The next thing I wanna do is define the
那么考虑全局的子集A，我将定义
concept of an event. So consider a subset
A of our universe And I, I'll define the
子集A的概率，即为其各个元素的权重和
probability of the subsets to be simply
the sum of the weights of all the elements
换句话说，我把A中所有元素X的概率权重相加
in the set A. In other words, I'm summing
over all X and A, the weights of these
因为整个全局的权重和应为1
elements X in the set A, Now because the
sum over the entire universe of all
如果我们求和，如果你看全局的概率
weights needs to be one. This means that
if we sum, well if you look at the
我们会得到1。如果我们看一个子集的
probability of the entire universe,
basically we get one. And if we look at
概率，我们会得到某个数
the probability of a subset of the
universe, we're gonna get some number in
在区间[0,1]里。我们说集合A的概率
the interval zero to one. And we say that
the probability of this set A, is the sum
是一个介于0和1的和
告诉大家，全局的子集A
which is a number between zero and one.
And I'll tell you that a subset A of the
叫做一个事件，集合A的概率叫做
universe is called an event. And the
probability of the set A is called the
事件的概率。我们看一个简单例子
probability of that event. So let's look
at a simple example. So suppose we look at
我们看全局U，为全体8位字符串，对吧？
the universe U, which consists of all
8-bit strings, right? So the size of this
那么全局U的大小为256
因为有256个8位字符串
universe U is 256 because there are 256
8-bit strings. Essentially we're looking
我们本质上在看所有字节值，共256种
现在我们定义以下事件
at all byte values, all 256 possible byte
values. Now let's define the following
事件包含于全局中
event. Basically the event is gonna
contain all bytes so all [inaudible]
所有低两位为11的字符串
extremes in the universe such that the two
least significant bits of the byte happens
例如，字符串01011010是全局中的元素
to be eleven. So for example, if we look at
01011010 that's an element in the universe
但不在集合A中。但如果我们把这个0
改成1，那它就是全局中
that's not in the set A, but if we choose
a zero to a one. Then that's an element of
集合A的元素了。现在我们来看看全局U上的
the universe which gives in our set A. And
now let's look at the uniform distribution
均匀分布，问大家这个事件A的概率是多少？
over the universe U and let me ask you
what is the probability of the, of the
那么如果我们随机选择一个字节
event A? So what is the probability that
when we choose a random byte, the two
低两位正好是11的概率是多少？
least significant bits of that byte
happens to be one, one? Well the answer is
答案是1/4，原因并不难找到
one-fourth, and the reason that's true is
because it's not too difficult to convince
256个字符串中，有64个满足要求
yourself that of the 256 eight bit
strings, exactly 64 of them, one quarter
有1/4的字符串结尾为11。那么概率是？
of them, end in one, one. And the
probability of each string is, we're
我们看的是均匀分布，每个字符串的概率
looking at the uniform distribution or
probability of each string is exactly one
严格地为1/|U|，即1/256
over the size of the universe, mainly one
over 256. And the product of these, you
这些的乘积，64个元素，每个有1/256
know, 64 elements, each one has weight one
over 256 is exactly one-fourth, which is
答案为1/4，即事件A的概率
概率中有一个非常简单的上界
the probability of the event A that we're
looking at. So a very simple bound on the
叫做并集上界。假设我们有两个事件A1和A2
probability of events is called the union
bound. So imagine we have two events A1
它们都是全局U的子集
我们想知道
and A2. So these are both subsets of some
universe U. And we wanna know what is the
A1或A2发生的概率。换句话说
probability that either A1 occurs, or A2
occurs. In other words, what is the
两事件的并集的概率是多少？
probability of the union of these two
events? This little U here denotes the
这个小U形表示两集合的并集
那么并集上界告诉我们
union of the two sets. So the union bound
tells us that the probability that either
A1或A2发生的概率不大于各概率和
A1 occurs or A2 occurs is basically less
than the sum of the two probabilities. And
(此处应为 no more than)
这是容易理解的
那么简单看一下这张图
that's actually quite easy to see. So
simply look at this picture here, you can
当我们看这两个概率的和时
see that when we look at, at the sum of
the two probabilities, we're basically
我们基本上是把A1中的元素的概率
summing the probability of all the
elements in A1, all the elements in A2 And
A2中的元素的概率加起来
交集部分我们重复计算了
you realized, we kind of double-summed
these elements in the intersection. They
右边求和时它们算了两次
结果就是，两个概率之和
get summed twice here on the right hand
side. And as a result, the sum of the two
实际上不小于A1和A2
probabilities is going to be larger or
larger than or equal to, the actual
并集的概率。这是经典并集上界
probability of the union of A1 and A2. So
that's the classic union bound. And in fact
事实上如果两个事件不相交
I'll tell you that if the two events are
disjoint, in other words they're
或说它们的交集为空，我们再求和的话
intersection is empty, in that case if we
look at the sum, at the probability that
A1或A2发生的概率就严格等于两概率之和
either A-1 or A02 happens, that's exactly
equal to the sum of the two probabilities.
怎么样？整个课程我们将使用这些事实
Okay? So we'll use these facts here and
there throughout the course. So just to be
弄清楚这里的不等式恒成立
但是当两事件不相交时
clear, the inequality holds always. But
when the two events are disjoint, then in
实际上这里我们可以取等号
那么让我们看一个简单例子
fact we get an equality over here. So
let's look at a simple example. Suppose
假设事件A1是全体n位以11结尾的字符串
our, event A1 is the set of all n-bit
strings that happen to end in 1-1. And
事件A2是全体n位以11开头的字符串的集合
suppose A2 is the set of all n-bit strings
that happen to begin with 1-1. Okay, so N
那么N可以设定为H或某个大数
我问如下事件的概率是多少？
thinks of it as H or some large number and
I'm asking that what is the probability
事件为A1或A2发生。换句话说
that either a one happens or a two
happens. In other words if I sample
如果我们从全局U中均匀地取样，低二位为11或
uniformly from the universe U, what is the
probability that either the least
高二位为11的概率是多少？
significant bits are one, one or the most
significant digits are one, one. Well as
就像刚才说的，就是A1并A2的概率
we said that's basically the probability
of the union of A1 and A2. We know that
我们知道每一个事件的概率是1/4
the probability of each one of these
events is one-quarter by what we just did
我们刚刚在上一张里算过。所以根据并集上界，
这里这个"或"的概率
on the previous slide. And therefore by the union
bound the probability of the
就是A1的概率1/4加上
'or'. Is, you know, a quarter of
the probability of A1, plus the
A2的概率1/4，等于1/4+1/4。我们这就证明了
probability of A2, which is a quarter plus
a quarter. And we just proved that the
11开头或11结尾的概率
probability of seeing 1-1 in the most
significant bit, or 1-1 least significant
比1/2小。所以这是一个简单的例子
bit, is less than one-half. So that's a
simple example of how we might go about
让我们用并集上界来估算概率的上界
using the Union Bound to bound the
probability that one of two events might
即两个事件之一发生。我们的下一概念
happen. The next concept we need to
define, is what's called a random
叫做随机变量。目前随机变量是比较直观的
variable. Now, random variables are fairly
intuitive objects. But unfortunately the
但很不幸，随机变量的形式化定义不好理解
formal definition of a random variable can
be a little confusing. So what I'll do
我将给一个例子，以期说明白点
is, I'll give an example, and hopefully
that will be clear enough. So formally, a
形式化地，一个随机变量记为X
它是一个从全局到某个集合V的函数
random variable denoted say, by X. Is a
function, from the universe into some set
集合V是随机变量取值的地方
V And we say that this set V is where the
random variable takes its values. So let's
我们来看一个特殊的例子
假定我们有一随机变量X
look at a particular example. So suppose
we have a random variable X. And this
这个随机变量映射到集合｛0, 1｝
那么该随机变量的取值
random variable maps into the set 01. So
the values of this random variable are
为0或1。也就是1位。这个随机变量
going to be either zero or one. So, one
bit, basically. Now, this random variable
以我们的全局，即n位二元字符串
｛0,1｝^n为映射的定义域
maps our universe, which is the set of
all n bit binary strings, 01 to the n.
怎么做到的？给定全局中的一个特殊样本
And how does it do it? Well, given a
particular sample in the universe, a
特定的n位字符串y
随机变量只要简单地输出
particular n-bit string y. What the
random variable will do is simply output
字符串y的最低位即可
这就是整个随机变量
the least significant bit of y. And that's
it. That's the whole random variable. So,
那么我问大家：假定有一均匀分布
now let me ask you. Suppose we look at a
uniform distribution on the set zero one
在集合｛0,1｝^n上，问随机变量
to the n. Let me ask you what is the
probability that this random variable
输出0的概率是多少？输出1的概率是多少？
output zero and what is the probability
that a random variable outputs one? Well
你可以看到答案是一半对一半。
让我们来推一推，为什么是这样
you can see that the answers are half and
half. Well let's just reason through
这张图展示了全局的情况
why that's the case. So here we have a
picture showing the universe and the
以及可能的输出空间。这时变量可能输出0或1
possible output space. And so in this case
the variable can output a zero or a one.
当变量输出0时
When there is a variable output zero,
there is a variable output zero when the
样本字符串的最低位为0
sample in the universe happens to be, to
have its least significant bit
变量为1时，样本字符串的最低位
be set to zero. In variable one, output
one when the sample in the universe
为1。好的，当均匀、随机选择字符串时
happens to have its least significant bit
set to one. Well, if choose strings
我们选到最低位为0的概率
uniformly at random, the probability that
we choose a string that has its least
严格等于1/2。随机变量输出0的概率
significant bits set to zero is exactly
one half. Which the random variable output
严格等于1/2。类似地，当随机选择
zero with a probability of exactly
one-half. Similarly, if we choose a random
n位字符串时，最低位为1的概率
n-bit string, the probability that the
least significant bit is equal to one is
也是1/2。所以我们说随机变量输出1
also one-half. And so we say that the
random variable output's one, also with
概率严格为1/2。更一般地
exactly probability of one-half. Now,
more generally, if we have a random
如果我们有特定集合V上的随机变量
这个随机变量实际上可推出
variable taking values in a certain set v,
then this random variable actually induces
集合V上的概率分布。这里
我们以符号形式表示其分布的意义
a distribution on this set v. And here, I
just wrote a, kind of a, in symbols, what
这其实是很好解释的。本质上
this distribution means. But it's actually
very easy to explain. Essentially, what it
随机变量输出v。以同样的概率
says is that the variable outputs v.
Basically, with the same probability that
如果我们从全局中随机取样
if we sample a random element in the
universe, and, and then we apply the
然后应用函数X。问函数结果等于v的可能性
function X. We ask, how likely is it that
the output is actually equal to v? So formally
形式化地，我们说X输出v的概率
等于当我们从全局中
we say that the probability that X outputs
v, is the same as the probability of the
随机取样时，落在v的原像中的概率
event that when we sample a random element
in the universe, we fall into the pre
如果这样还不清楚，也不重要
image of v under the function X. And again,
if this wasn't clear, it's not that
你只需要知道随机变量从特定集合V取值
important. All you need to know is that a
random variable takes values in a
可推导出集合V上的概率分布
particular set V, and in, induces a
distribution on that set V. Now there's a
有一个特别重要的随机变量叫均匀随机变量
particularly important random variable
called a uniform random variable. And it's
它正如你期望的那样定义。那么
我们说U是某有限集
basically defined as you would expect. So
let's say that U is some finite
比如是全体N位二进制字符串
set. For example the set of all N bit
binary strings, and we're gonna denote a
我们记一个随机变量R
R从U中均匀地取样
random variable R that's basically
sample's uniformly from the set U by this
用这个有点好玩的箭头加上R来表示
little funny arrow with a little R on top
of it. In this, again the notes that the
注意随机变量R是U上的均匀随机变量
random variable R is literally a uniform
random variable sampled over the set U. So
符号意义是，对于全局中的所有元素a
in symbols what's this means is that for
all elements a in the universe, the
r等于a的概率就是1/|U|
如果你想坚持使用
probability that R is equal to A is simply
R one over U. And if you want to stick to
均匀随机变量的定义，虽不要紧
the formal definition of a, of a uniform
variable, it's not actually that important
但我想说均匀随机变量从形式上看
But I would just say that formally the
uniform random variable is an identity
是恒等函数，R(X)等于X
function namely R [inaudible] is equal to
X for all X in the universe. So just to see
为了看得更清楚些，我问大家一个问题
that this is clear, let me ask you a
simple puzzle. Suppose we have a uniform
我们有一个2位字符串的均匀随机变量
所以集合为｛01，10，00，11｝
random variable over 2-bit strings, so
over the set, 01, ten, one and now, let's
我们定义一个新的随机变量X
它将R的第一位和第二位加起来
define a new random variable X to basically
sum the first and second bits of R. That
X就是R1+R2，将第一、第二位的整数相加
is, X simply is the sum of R1 and R2, the
first and second bits of R, treating those
比如，如果r正好是00，那么X=0+0=0
bits as integers. So, for example, if, r
happens to be 00, then x will be zero+0,
问一下，X=2的概率是多少？
which is zero. So let me ask you, what is
the probability that x is = to two? So
不难看出答案是1/4
it's not difficult to see that the answer
is exactly, one-fourth because, basically
因为X等于2当且仅当两位都是1
the only way that x is equal to two is if
r happens to be 1,1 but the probability
但两位都是1的概率是1/4
that r is equal to 1,1 is basically
one-fourth because r is uniform over the
因为R是均匀分布在2位字符串集合上的
本节我最后想定义的概念是
set of all two bit stings. The last
concept I want to define in this segment
随机算法。我肯定大家都熟悉
is what's called a randomized algorithm.
So I'm sure you're all familiar with
确定算法。这些算法给定输入数据
deterministic algorithms. These are
algorithms that basically take a
它们的输出总是一致的，不妨记为Y
particular, input data, as input, and they
always produce the same output, say Y. So
所以如果我们运行这种算法100次
给定相同输入，我们总能得到
if we run the algorithm a hundred times on
the same input, we'll always get the same
相同的输出。所以你可以把确定算法视为函数
output. So you can think of a
deterministic algorithm as a function that
给定输入数据M，总会产生严格相同的输出
given a particular input data, M, will
always produce exactly the same output, A
A(M)。随机算法有点不同，与之前相同
of M. A randomized algorithm is a little
different, in that, as before, it takes
都是取数据M为输入，不过还有一个隐形参数R
the input data M as input, but it also
has an implicit argument called R, where
每次算法运行时，R都重新取样
this R is sampled anew every time the
algorithm is run. And in particular this R
特别地，R每次从N位字符串里均匀取样
is sampled uniformly at random from the
set of all N-bit strings, for some
N任意指定。我们每次输入M，运行算法
arbitrary N. Now what happens is every
time we run the algorithm on a particular
我们会获得不同的输出
因为R每次生成的不一样
input M we're gonna get a different output
because a different R is generated every
所以第一次我们运行得到一个输出
time. So the first time we run the
algorithm we get one output. The second
第二次我们运行，生成了一个新的R
我们得到一个不同的输出
time we run the algorithm a new R is
generated and we get a different output.
第三次我们运行，生成了一个新的R
我们得到第三个输出
The third time we run the algorithm a new
R is generated and we get a third output
等等。可以把随机算法想象成
and so on. So really the way to think
about a randomized algorithm is it's
定义了一个随机变量，对吧？
给定了一个特定输入信息M
actually defining a random variable.
Right? So given a particular input
就定义了一个随机变量
message, M, it's defining a random
variable which is, defining a distribution
定义了所有的这个算法可能输出集合上的一个分布。
给定输入M
over the set of all possible outputs
of this algorithm, given the input, M. So
记住随机算法的输出每次运行都会变
the thing to remember is that the output
of a randomized algorithm changes every
事实上，这种算法定义了一个分布
time you run it. And in fact, the algorithm
defines a distribution and the set of all
以及全体可能输出的集合
让我们来看一个特例
possible outputs. So let's look at a
particular example. So suppose we have a
我们有一随机算法，输入信息M
randomized algorithm that takes as input a
message M. And of course it also takes an
当然还有隐性输入，用于随机操作的字符串
implicit input which is this random
string that is used to randomize its
那么这个算法就会加密信息M
operation. So now what the algorithm will
do is simply will encrypt the message M
使用随机生成的字符串作为输入
所以这就定义了一个随机变量
using the random string as input. So this
basically defines a random variable. This
这个随机变量从信息M的加密结果里取值
random variable takes values that are
encryptions of the message M. And really
这个随机变量其实是定义在全体
what this random, random variable is it's
a distribution over the set of all
信息M的可能加密结果上的分布
密钥则是均匀分布的
possible encryptions of the message M
under a uniform key. So the main point to
要记住的要点是，即使随机算法的输入
remember is that even though the inputs to
a randomized algorithm might always be the
总是一致，每次运行也会得到不同的结果
same every time you run the randomized
algorithm you're gonna get a different
好的，这一节讲完
output. Okay So, that concludes this
segment, and we'll see a bit more discrete
下一节我们继续讨论离散概率
probability in the next segment.